A Finding Aid to the Jacques Lipchitz papers and Bruce Bassett papers concerning Jacques Lipchitz, 1910-2001, bulk 1941-2001, in the Archives of American Art AAA.lipcjacq2
Archives of American Art
- Jacques Lipchitz papers, bulk 1941-1999; circa 1910-1999; Series 1; 9.5 Linear feet Boxes 1-10, OV 11-12; Bassett, Bruce W.; Lipchitz, Jacques, 1891-1973
  - Catalogue Raisonné records, 1992-1999; 1.5; 1.7 Linear feet Boxes 5-7, 10
    1.5.3: Volumes 1 and 2, circa 1992-1999
    - Volume One: The Paris Years, 1910-1940, 1992-1996; 1.5.1
      Correspondence includes photo requests and permissions.
      Administrative correspondence is arranged chonologically, and research correspondence is arranged alphabetically by correspondent or institution. All other materials are filed chronologically within folders. The manuscript of an addendum to volume 1 (published in volume 2) is found among the records relating to the second volume. This subseries has not been scanned.
      - Manuscript (Box 5)
        - Text by Alan G. Wilkinson, circa 1995-1996 (Box 5, Folder 36)
        - Introduction by A. M. Hammacher, "Jacques Lipchitz, 1891-1973: A Concise Survey" (1987-1988), circa 1995-1996 (Box 5, Folder 37)
      - Dummies (Box 5)
        - First Version, Corrected, circa 1996 (Box 5, Folder 38)
        - Early Version (incomplete, plates only), circa 1996 (Box 5, Folder 39)
        - Complete Copy, Corrected, circa 1996 (Box 5, Folder 40)
      - Proof Sheets, Corrected, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 41)
        Oversized material housed in Box 10, F6-9
      - Addendum to Volume One: The Paris Years, 1910-1940, 1999 (Box 5, Folder 42)
        Material housed in Box 6, F15
      - Correspondence, Administrative, 1994-1995 (Box 5, Folder 43)
      - Correspondence, Administrative, 1996 January-April (Box 5, Folder 44)
      - Correspondence, Administrative, 1996 May-June (Box 5, Folder 45)
      - Correspondence, Administrative, 1996 July-September (Box 5, Folder 46)
      - Correspondence, Research (Box 6)
        - Albright-Knox Art Gallery - Barnes Foundation, 1992-1996 (Box 6, Folder 1)
          Albright-Knox Art Gallery
          Art Gallery of Ontario
          Baltimore Museum of Art
        - Bunkamura Museum of Art - Indianapolis Museum of Art, 1995-1996 (Box 6, Folder 2)
          Bunkamura Museum of Art
          Chrysler Museum of Art
          Contemporary Arts Museum, Houston
          Dallas Museum of Art
          Dartmouth College, Hood Museum of Art
          Galerie Jeanne Boucher
          Hirshhorn Museum and Sculpture Garden
          Indianapolis Museum of Art
        - The Israel Museum, 1995-1996 (Box 6, Folder 3)
        - Kansas City Art Institute, Kemper Museum - Princeton University, The Art Museum, 1992-1996 (Box 6, Folder 4)
          Kansas City Art Institute, Kemper Museum of Contemporary Art and Design
          Kunsthaus Zürich
          Los Angeles County Museum of Art
          Museé des Beaux Arts, Rouen
          Museum of Modern Art
          Milwaukee Art Museum
          Princeton University, The Art Museum
      - Notes and Research Materials (Box 6)
        - Notes and Printed Material, circa 1990s (Box 6, Folder 5)
        - Photographs of Work (created 1910-1916), circa 1990s (Box 6, Folder 6)
        - Photographs of Work (created 1933-1940), circa 1990s (Box 6, Folder 7)
        - Negatives of Work (created 1910-1936), circa 1990s (Box 6, Folder 8)
        - Color Transparencies of Work (created 1911-1936), circa 1990s (Box 6, Folder 9)
      - Proof Sheets, Corrected, 1996; 4 Folders (Box 10, Folder 6-9)
        Oversized material from Box 5, F41
    - Volume 2: The American Years, 1941-1973, circa 1992-1999; 1.5.2
      Administrative correspondence is mainly between Marlborough Gallery staff and the author, Alan G. Wilkinson.
      Research correspondence includes several letters received in response to inquiries made during preparation of volume 1 that also contain information about works produced after 1940. They were used for researching volume 2 and remain with the records relating to its compilation.
      Research correspondence is arranged alphabetically by correspondent or institution and all other materials are filed chronologically within each folder. This subseries has not been scanned.
      - Manuscript (Box 6)
        - "Preface, With Notes on Casting" (draft and corrected version), 1999 (Box 6, Folder 10)
        - Catalogue Entries, First Draft, 1999 (Box 6, Folder 11)
        - Catalogue Entries, Revised (June 11), 1999 (Box 6, Folder 12)
        - Catalogue Entries, Revised (June 26), 1999 (Box 6, Folder 13)
        - Title Page, Acknowledgements, Bibliography, 1999 (Box 6, Folder 14)
        - "Addendum to Volume One: The Paris Years, 1910-1940" "Addendum to Lipchitz Bibliography/Chronology,", 1999 (Box 6, Folder 15)
          Material from Box 5, F42
      - Proof Sheets, Preface, 1999 (Box 6, Folder 16)
      - Correspondence, Administrative, 1998 (Box 6, Folder 17)
      - Correspondence, Administrative, 1999 January-March (Box 6, Folder 18)
      - Correspondence, Administrative, 1999 April-June (Box 6, Folder 19)
      - Correspondence, Research (Box 6)
        - Albright-Knox Art Gallery - Currier Gallery of Art, 1995-1999 (Box 6, Folder 20)
          Birmingham Museum of Art
          Christie's, Tel Aviv
          Cincinnati Art Museum
          Columbia University
          Cornell University, Herbert F. Johnson Museum
          Currier Gallery of Art
        - Dallas Museum of Art - Solomon R. Guggenheim Museum, 1995-1999 (Box 6, Folder 21)
          Des Moines Art Center
          Detroit Institute of Arts
          Fairmount Park Art Association
          Galeria Nazionale d'Arte Moderne, Rome
        - Haags Gemeentemuseum - Israel Museum, 1995-1999 (Box 6, Folder 22)
          Haags Gemeentemuseum
          Hakone Open Art Museum
          Hirshhorn Museum and Sculpture Garden, Smithsonian Institution
          Honolulu Academy of Arts
          Indiana University Art Museum
        - Jewish Museum - Los Angeles County Museum of Art, 1998-1999 (Box 6, Folder 23)
        - Massachusetts Institute of Technology - Museé d'art et d'histoire du Judiasme, 1993-1999 (Box 6, Folder 24)
          Massachusetts Institute of Technology, List Visual Arts Center
          Minnesota Museum of American Art
          Munson-Williams-Proctor Institute, Museum of Art
          Museé d'art et d'histoire du Judiasme
        - Museo de Arte Contemporaneo - The Museum of Modern Art, 1998-1999 (Box 6, Folder 25)
          Museo de Arte Contemporaneo, Caracas
          Museo de Bellas Artes, Caracas
          Museum Boijmans Van Beuningen
          Museum Folkwang Essen
          Museum Moderner Kunst Stiftung Ludwig Wein
          Museum of Fine Arts, Houston
        - National Gallery of Canada - Princeton University, Art Museum, 1992-1999 (Box 6, Folder 26)
          National Gallery of Canada
          Nelson-Atkins Museum of Art
          Niigata City Museum
          Norton Simon Museum/Norton Museum of Art
          Open Air Museum of Sculpture
          Owen, Jane Blaffer and R. L. Blaffer Trust
          Philadelphia Museum of Art
          Portland Art Museum (OR)
        - San Francisco Museum of Modern Art - Stedelijk Museum, 1995-1999 (Box 6, Folder 27)
          San Francisco Museum of Modern Art
          Scottish National Gallery of Modern Art
          Scottsdale Museum of Contemporary Art
          Sheldon Memorial Art Gallery and Sculpture Garden
          Shizuoka Perfectual Museum of Art
          Skirball Cultural Center and Museum
          Southern Methodist University, Meadows Museum
          Staatliche Kunsthalle Karlsruhe
          Städtische Kunsthalle Mannheim
          Stanford University, Iris and B. Gerald Cantor Center for Visual Arts
          Stedelijk Museum
        - Sttatsgalerie Stuttgart - University of California, 1998-1999 (Box 6, Folder 28)
          Sttatsgalerie Stuttgart
          Syracuse University Art Collection
          Tel Aviv Museum of Art
          Tokushima Modern Art Museum
          University of Arizona Museum of Art
          University of California, Los Angeles, Franklin D Murphy Sculpture Garden
        - University of Chicago - Virginia Museum of Fine Arts, 1995-1999 (Box 6, Folder 29)
          University of Chicago, The David and Alfred Smart Museum of Art
          University of Iowa Museum of Art
          University of Michigan Museum of Art
          University of Minnesota, Tweed Museum of Art
        - Walker Art Center - Worcester Art Museum, 1995-1999 (Box 6, Folder 30)
          Walker Art Center
          Washington University
          Wellesley College, Davis Museum and Cultural Center
          Whitney Museum of American Art
          Worcester Art Museum
      - Notes and Research Materials (Box 6)
        - Exhibition Catalogs (1942-1957, photocopies), circa 1995-1999 (Box 6, Folder 31)
        - Exhibition Catalogs (1959-1982, photocopies), circa 1995-1999 (Box 6, Folder 32)
        - Notes and Lists, circa 1995-1999 (Box 6, Folder 33)
        - Photographs of Sculpture (Box 6)
          - Created in 1941-1947, circa 1990s; 5 Folders (Box 6, Folder 34-38)
          - Created in 1948-1954, circa 1990s; 5 Folders (Box 6, Folder 39-43)
          - Created in 1955-1972, circa 1990s; 6 Folders (Box 6, Folder 44-49)
        - Negatives of Sculpture (Box 7)
          - Created in 1941-1947/48, circa 1990s (Box 7, Folder 1)
          - Created in 1952-1958, circa 1990s (Box 7, Folder 2)
          - Created in 1970-1971/72, circa 1990s (Box 7, Folder 3)
        - Color Transparencies of Sculpture Created in 1941-1971/72, circa 1990s (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Volumes One and Two, circa 1992-1999; 1.5.3
      Research materials used for both volumes of the catalogue raisonné consist of unidentified images of Lipchitz's sculpture and copies of inventory cards for bronzes and stone sculptures at Marlborough Gallery, Inc.
      Several letters received in response to inquiries made during preparation of volume 1 also contain information about works produced after 1940. They were used for researching volume 2 and remain with the research correspondence documenting its compilation.
      This subseries has not been scanned.
      - Research Materials, Marlborough Gallery, Inc. (Box 7)
        - Images of Lipchitz Bronzes and Stone Sculptures, Unidentified, circa 1960s-1990s (Box 7, Folder 5)
        - Inventory Cards for Lipchitz Bronzes and Stone Sculptures, circa 1960s-1990s (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Financial records, 1942-1968; 1.6; 0.2 Linear feet Box 7
    Account statements issued by Buchholz Gallery and Curt Valentin Gallery record works sold, buyers, and prices. They also document the charges to the artist for casting, photography, insurance, and etc. Records concerning the Lipchitz Collection consist of receipts from auctioneers and galleries.
    Additional financial records including gallery accounts, insurance records, and invoices and receipts enclosed with letters are scattered throughout the correspondence (Subseries 1.2). Notes on expenses are scattered throughout the diaries (Subseries 1.3).
    This series, arranged by record type, has been partially scanned. Records concerning banking, insurance, and taxes have not been scanned.
    - Accounts, 1942-1955 (Box 7, Folder 7)
      Curt Valentin Gallery
    - Banking Records and List of Accounts, 1951-1959 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Insurance, 1952-1960 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Invoices and Receipts (Box 7)
      - Casting and Finishing, 1951-1968 (Box 7, Folder 10)
      - Expenses, Miscellaneous, 1952-1968 (Box 7, Folder 11)
      - Framing, 1952-1968 (Box 7, Folder 12)
      - Lipchitz Art Collection, 1944-1964 (Box 7, Folder 13)
      - Photography, 1952-1967 (Box 7, Folder 14)
      - Shipping, Storage, Customs, 1942-1960 (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Jacques Lipchitz Studio Fund, circa 1960s-1970s (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - Taxes, 1954-1957 (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - Notes, Miscellaneous, 1961-1963 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Artwork, circa 1950s-1970s; 1.7; 2 Folders Box 7
    Sketches by Lipchitz consist of pencil drawings on the back of an envelope and drawings in ball point pen on two small slips of paper. The geometric designs by an unidentified artist are rendered in ink on two sheets of graph paper.
    A few additional rough sketches, often on the backs of envelopes or letters, are scattered throughout Lipchitz's correspondence (Subseries 1.2). Similar sketches are found in some of his diaries (Subseries 1.3). This series has been scanned in its entirety.
    - Sketches by Lipchitz, circa 1950s-1970s (Box 7, Folder 19)
    - Geometric Designs by Unidentified Artist, circa 1950s-1970s (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Scrapbooks, 1945-1946; 1.8; 0.01 Linear feet Box 7
    Two volumes consist mainly of newspaper clippings and a small number of clippings from periodicals mentioning Lipchitz and/or containing reproductions of his work. All clippings were provided by the French clipping service Le Lynx. Volume 2 also includes a 2-page transcript of a very brief interview, and the text of equally brief remarks delivered by Lipchitz at an unidentified event. Material preserved in the scrapbooks is mostly in French, with a few items in German and English.
    This series has been scanned in its entirety.
    - Volume 1, 1945 (Box 7, Folder 21)
    - Volume 2, 1946 (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Printed Material, 1929-1973; 1.9; 1 Linear feet Boxes 7-8, 10, OV 12
    Exhibition catalogs and announcements, articles, press releases, books, reproductions, and programs document Lipchitz's exhibitions, sculpture, commissions, the Lipchitz Collection, and events honoring the sculptor. This series also contains a variety of printed material including newspaper clippings and other miscellaneous items regarding general art topics. Some items are in German and French.
    Additional printed items are found enclosed with correspondence (Subseries 1.2) and, to a lesser extent, in his diaries (Subseries 1.3). Both scrapbooks (Subseries 1.8) are comprised mainly of newspaper clippings.
    This series is organized into 2 subseries. This series has been partially scanned. General art-related material not related to Lipchitz have not been scanned.
    1.9.1: About/Mentioning Lipchitz, 1929-1973
    1.9.2: Art-related, 1944-1969
    - About/Mentioning Lipchitz, 1929-1973; 1.9.1
      Architectural prints show sites for commissions and/or details of projects. Miscellaneous items consist of a ship passenger list, the menu of a farewell dinner honoring Lipchitz, and a general brochure about The American Academy of Arts and Letters containing a picture of Lipchitz receiving an award. Programs are for events honoring Lipchitz and a 1967 Jacques Lipchitz Festival sponsored by the Hastings Creative Arts Council.
      Architectural prints are arranged alphabetically by commission and books are alphabetized by author. Otherwise, items within folders are arranged chronologically.
      This subseries has been partially scanned. Reproductions have not been scanned. Only the cover, title page, and relevant pages have been scanned from catalogs of group exhibitions, museum publications, newsletters, and etc. For contemporary published items that are widely available in libraries, only the covers and title pages have been scanned.
      - Advertisements for Exhibitions, circa 1960s (Box 7, Folder 23)
      - Architectural Prints (sites for Lipchitz commissions), 1958-1964 (Box 7, Folder 24)
        Oversized material housed in OV 12
        Blaffer Trust Shrine, New Harmony, IN
        International Business Machines, Yorktown Heights, NY
        St. Louis, Lambert Airport
        University of Minnesota, Duluth
        Washington Square East, Philadelphia
      - Articles, 1955-1972 (Box 7, Folder 25)
      - Books (Box 7)
        - Goldwater, Robert. Lipchitz. Amsterdam: Allert de Lange, 1954 (Box 7, Folder 26)
          partially scanned
        - Raynal, Maurice. Jacques Lipchitz. Paris: Éditions Jeanne Bucher, (partially scanned), [1947] (Box 7, Folder 27)
        - Les Sculpteurs Français Nouveaux No. 7, Jacques Lipchitz, Paris: ??ditions de la Nouvelle Revue Française, 1929 (Box 7, Folder 28)
      - Exhibition Catalogs and Announcements (Box 7)
        - Lipchitz Solo and Group Exhibitions, 1930-1949 (Box 7, Folder 29)
        - Lipchitz Solo and Group Exhibitions, 1950-1959 (Box 7, Folder 30)
        - Lipchitz Solo and Group Exhibitions, 1961-1963 (Box 7, Folder 31)
        - Lipchitz Solo and Group Exhibitions, 1964-1966 (Box 7, Folder 32)
        - Lipchitz Solo and Group Exhibitions, 1967-1969 (Box 7, Folder 33)
        - Lipchitz Solo and Group Exhibitions, 1970 (Box 7, Folder 34)
        - The Lipchitz Collection, 1960 (Box 7, Folder 35)
      - Lecture Announcements, 1954-1963 (Box 7, Folder 36)
      - Miscellaneous Items, 1962-1964 (Box 7, Folder 37)
      - Museum Publications, 1959 (Box 7, Folder 38)
      - Newsletters, 1966-1967 (Box 7, Folder 39)
      - Newspaper Clippings, 1931-1956 (Box 7, Folder 40)
      - Newspaper Clippings, 1957-1959 (Box 7, Folder 41)
      - Newspaper Clippings, 1960-1962 (Box 7, Folder 42)
      - Newspaper Clippings, 1963 (Box 7, Folder 43)
      - Newspaper Clippings, 1964 (Box 7, Folder 44)
      - Newspaper Clippings, 1965-1972 (Box 7, Folder 45)
      - Newspaper Clippings, circa 1931-1972 (Box 7, Folder 46)
      - Poem (photocopy) by Carol L. Kort, "In Memory of Jacques Lipchitz (1891-1973),", circa 1970s (Box 7, Folder 47)
      - Press Releases, 1952-1972 (Box 7, Folder 48)
      - Programs, 1959-1967 (Box 7, Folder 49)
      - Reproductions (Box 8)
        - Twelve Bronzes by Jacques Lipchitz; 16 Collotype Plates with Introductory Note (portfolio), 1943 (Box 8, Folder 1)
        - Postcards, circa 1950s-1970s (Box 8, Folder 2)
        - Unidentified Publication (fragment), circa 1950s-1970s (Box 8, Folder 3)
      - Exhibition Catalog, 1970 (Box 10, Folder 1)
        Oversized material scanned with Box 7, F34
      - Architectural Prints, 1958-1964 (Box OV 12)
        Oversized material scanned with Box 7, F24
    - Art-related, 1944-1969; 1.9.2
      This subseries consists of a variety of printed items on general art topics, none referencing Lipchitz or his art collection.
      This subseries has been not been scanned.
      - Articles about Primitive and Ancient Art, circa 1960s (Box 8, Folder 4)
      - Books on Miscellaneous Art Topics, 1944 (Box 8, Folder 5)
      - Exhibition Catalogs and Announcements (Box 8)
        - Other Artists, 1945-1969; 2 Folders (Box 8, Folder 6-7)
        - Primitive and Ancient Art, 1953-1963 (Box 8, Folder 8)
      - Miscellaneous Items, 1949-1963 (Box 8, Folder 9)
      - Museum Publication, 1959 (Box 8, Folder 10)
        Oversized material housed in Box 10, F1
      - Newsletters, 1955-1966 (Box 8, Folder 11)
      - Newspaper Clippings (Box 8)
        - Other Artists, 1959-1966 (Box 8, Folder 12)
        - Primitive and Ancient Art, 1962-1964 (Box 8, Folder 13)
        - Miscellaneous Art Topics, 1952-1967 (Box 8, Folder 14)
      - Reproductions of Sculpture and Primitive Art, circa 1950s-1970s (Box 8, Folder 15)
      - Museum Publication, 1959 (Box 10, Folder 1)
        Oversized material from Box 8, F10
  - Photographs, circa 1910s-1967; 1.10; 1.7 Linear feet Boxes 8-10
    Photographs document people, artwork, project sites and models, exhibition installations, events, and places. Photographs of people include Jacques Lipchitz, family members, and others. Photographs of artwork include pieces by both Jacques Lipchitz and other artists. Views of Lipchitz exhibition installations in the United States and Europe mainly document solo shows. Photographs of events record a variety of occasions, among them: the opening of Lipchitz's new studio at Hastings-on-Hudson, NY; the dedication ceremony for Philip Johnson's Roofless Church in New Harmony, IN, with ornamental gates and a sculpture by Lipchitz; and Lipchitz addressing an anatomy class at Albert Einstein Medical College. Among the photographs of places are Lipchitz's studios at Hastings-on-Hudson, NY, and Pietrasanta, Italy, and a view of Pablo Picasso's Paris studio.
    Additional photographs enclosed with letters are scattered among the correspondence (Subseries 1.2). Research materials amassed during the course of compiling both volumes of the The Sculpture of Jacques Lipchitz: A Catalogue Raisonné (Subseries 1.5) include photographs, negatives, and color transparencies of his sculpture.
    This series has been paritally scanned. Blank versos of photographs, photographs of artwork, negatives, slides and color transparencies have not been scanned.
    The series is arranged as 8 subseries:
    1.10.1: People, circa 1910s-1967
    1.10.2: Artwork, circa 1910s-1962
    1.10.3: Project Sites and Models, circa 1950s-1970s
    1.10.4: Exhibition Installations, 1950-1961
    1.10.5: Events, circa 1952-1966
    1.10.6: Places, 1956-1964
    1.10.7: Photograph Album, 1967
    1.10.8: Negatives, Slides, and Color Transparencies, circa 1950s-1965
    - People, circa 1910s-1967; 1.10.1
      Photographs of Jacques Lipchitz include a small head shot taken during his early years in Paris, copies of two 1946 portraits by Arnold Newman, views of him in the Hastings-on-Hudson studio, at Modern Art Foundry, and with Yulla. Also found are views of the sculptor's hands.
      The Lipchitz family is represented by images of his parents Abraham and Rachel Krinsky Lipchitz, sister Diana, youngest brother Rubin, nephew Georgy Hay, a niece and her daughter. Most were tentatively identified in 2010 by Loyla Lipchitz.
      Among the other identified individuals are Josef Albers and Ken Tyler, Jane Blaffer Owen, and Fiore de Henriquez, a young sculptor who lived with the Lipchitz family in the mid 1960s. Photographs of Senator Robert A. Taft probably served as resource material for a bust commissioned circa 1958, and those of President Lyndon B. Johnson were likely used when Lipchitz designed the 1964 Presidential Scholar Medal.
      Additional photographs of Lipchitz and others are found among photographs of events (Subseries 1.10.5), and some may be enclosed with letters, scattered throughout the correspondence (Subseries 1.2).
      Items within folders are arranged chronologically; undated items follow in rough chronological order. This subseries has been scanned in its entirety.
      - Jacques Lipchitz (Box 8)
        - By Arnold Newman, George Moffett, E. H. Roth, and unidentified photographers, circa 1910s-1964 (Box 8, Folder 16)
        - Hands of, circa 1950s-1970s (Box 8, Folder 17)
          Oversized material housed in Box 10, F2
      - Jacques Lipchitz in his Studio (Box 8)
        - Paris, circa 1912 (Box 8, Folder 18)
        - Hastings-on-Hudson, NY (photographers: The New York Times and unidentified), 1962-1967 (Box 8, Folder 19)
        - Hastings-on-Hudson, NY (photographers: Colton Photos, George Holton, George Moffett, Adolph Studley, William Vandivert, Whitestone Photos), circa 1960s (Box 8, Folder 20)
        - Hastings-on-Hudson, NY (photographers: Roloff Beny, F. Roy Kemp, George Moffett, Bert Van Bork, and unidentified), circa 1960s (Box 8, Folder 21)
      - Jacques Lipchitz at Foundry (Box 8)
        - Unidentified Foundry (George Moffett, photographer), circa 1960s (Box 8, Folder 22)
        - Modern Age Foundry (John C. Spring, photographer), circa 1960s (Box 8, Folder 23)
      - Jacques Lipchitz at Emiliano Sorini's Lithography Workshop (Marvin Bolotsky, photographer), 1962 (Box 8, Folder 24)
      - With Others (Box 8)
        - With Yulla Lipchitz, circa 1970s (Box 8, Folder 25)
        - With Unidentified Exhibition Juries, circa 1950s-1970s (Box 8, Folder 26)